Guide to the Civil War Posters 1861-1865 PR 55-3
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Poster File, Civil War Posters
1861-1865
PR 55-3
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.62 Linear feet (466 items)
The Civil War Posters collection at the New-York Historical Society forms part of the society's vast collection of posters, which is comprised of approximately 5,000 items. As part of this major poster collection, the Civil War posters, consisting mainly of recruiting posters, illustrate a variety of advertisements by Civil War regiments as they were designed to appeal to potential recruits in the early 1860s.
Provenance
The collection's accession dates span from the 1860s to 1937.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers, by appointment only.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Scope and Content Note
The Civil War Posters consist of a total of 466 items. Of this total, 275 are recruiting posters, 31 are posters advertising auctions, drives, meetings, and the remaining 160 items refer to deserter lists, muster rolls, and various other announcements and newspaper clippings pertaining to the Civil War. The recruiting posters represent a variety of Civil War regiments from the states of Maine, Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, and Pennsylvania in the areas of artillery, cavalry, and infantry. Most of the recruiting posters come from New York followed by New Jersey and Pennsylvania. Also noted on many recruiting posters are the types of men desired. These desired men may have been African Americans, Germans (11 are written in German), Irish, married or single men.
The iconography of the recruiting posters also makes them quite distinct. Icons, in color and black and white, depict the spreading wings of an eagle with banners, valiant cavalry men on horses, beautiful harps, and the heroic face of George Washington to name only a few. For many posters, it is the icon that is the prominent image on the poster and draws the viewer's attention. Other posters of interest may be found in the 160 items which are not recruiting posters. Some of these items include songs, poems, and even a hospital slipper pattern. The deserter lists in these 160 items demonstrate the indignance of officials against deserters and the posting of rewards to track down such persons.
Arrangement
The recruiting posters, the first 306 items of the Civil War posters collection, are numbered in an arrangement by state, event (meeting, auctions, etc.), size (standard vs. oversize), regiment designation, and title. The remaining 160 items (deserter lists, muster rolls, etc.), are divided between Union and Confederate and arranged by state. The posters are physically arranged by size. An item-level database is available in the repository.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other series of the Poster File contain similar items such as theater playbills and circus posters, book and magazine placards, war posters, and other political and cultural posters.
Baker & Godwin, printer; King & Baird, printer; Bounties, Military--United States; Maine--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories; Massachusetts--History --Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories; Military deserters; Military records; Military service, Voluntary--United States; Muster rolls; New Jersey--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories; New York (State)--History --Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories; Pennsylvania--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories; Prints; Rhode Island--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Posters; United States. Army--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.--Civil War, 1861-1865; United States. Army. Artillery--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; United States. Army. Cavalry--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; United States. Army. Infantry--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; United States. Army. Invalid Corps.--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; United States. Marine Corps--Recruiting, enlistment, etc.--Civil War, 1861-1865; War posters, American
- An item-level, searchable database of posters is available in the repository and at http://dlib.nyu.edu/nyhs/search/. The following folder list describes how posters are housed i.
  - Massachusetts, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, New York, 1861-1863 (Folder 1)
    General note
    #s 5, 16, 17, 51, 55, 64, 203, 264
  - Massachusetts, New Jersey, 1861-1865 (Folder 2)
    #s 2, 4, 12-15, 18-22
  - New Jersey, 1861-1864 (Folder 3)
    #s 23-28, 48-50, 52
  - New Jersey, 1861-1863 (Folder 4)
    #s 53, 54, 56, 57, 59-63, 65
  - Pennsylvania, 1861, undated (Folder 5)
    #s 255- 257, 259, 260, 262, 263, 265-267
  - Pennsylvania, 1861 (Folder 6)
    #s 268-275
  - Maine, Massachusetts, New Jersey, 1863-1864, undated (Folder 7)
    #s 1, 3, 6, 8, 30, 31, 33, 34, 36, 39
  - New Jersey, 1861-1863, undated (Folder 8)
    #s 58, 66, 68, 69, 76, 79-82, 84, 87
  - New Jersey, 1863-1864 (Folder 9)
    #s 90, 93-96, 98-100
  - New York, 1861-[1865] (Folder 10)
    #s 118, 127, 134, 136, 137, 141, 142, 162
  - Pennsylvania, 1861-1864 (Folder 11)
    #s 246, 247, 249, 250, 253, 254, 258, 261
  - Pennsylvania, 1862-1863, undated (Folder 12)
    #276, 282, 283-5, 287, 290, 294, 295, 300
  - Massachusetts, New Jersey, 1861-1864, undated (Folder 13)
    #s7, 9, 10, 29, 32, 35, 37, 38, 40
  - New Jersey, 1863-1865 (Folder 14)
    #s 41-47, 67, 70
  - New Jersey, 1861-1865, undated (Folder 15)
    #s 71-75, 77, 78
  - New Jersey, 1862-1863, undated (Folder 16)
    #s 83, 85, 86, 88, 89, 91, 92, 97
  - New Jersey, New York, 1861-1864, undated (Folder 17)
    #s 101, 103, 105-115
  - New York, [1863], undated (Folder 18)
    #s 116, 117, 119-126, 128
  - New York, [1863], undated (Folder 19)
    #s 129-133, 135, 138-140, 143
  - New York, undated (Folder 20)
    #s 144-153
  - New York, undated (Folder 21)
    #s 154-161, 163, 164
  - New York, undated (Folder 22)
    #s 165-174
  - New York, undated (Folder 23)
    #s 175-184
  - New York, undated (Folder 24)
    #s 185-195
  - New York, 1862, undated (Folder 25)
    #s 196-202, 204-206
  - Pennsylvania, New York, 1861-1863, undated (Folder 26)
    # 245, 248, 251, 252, 277-280, 282, 286
  - Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, 1861-1863, undated (Folder 27)
    #s 288, 289, 291-293, 296-299, 304, 305
  - New York, undated (Folder Oversize 1)
    #s 104, 207-226
  - Oversize: Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, 1862-1863, undated (Folder Oversize 2)
    #s 11, 102, 227-244, 301-303, 306